<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-06-14T03:08:03+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Sameer Kulkarni</title><subtitle>personal description</subtitle><author><name>Sameer Kulkarni</name><email>sameer@thekulkarni.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">0 to 100 (Hours of) Meditation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/2024/05/0-to-100-hours-of-meditation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="0 to 100 (Hours of) Meditation" /><published>2024-07-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/2024/05/0-to-100-hours-of-meditation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/2024/05/0-to-100-hours-of-meditation/"><![CDATA[<p>If I had a spirit animal, it would have probably been a “happy squirrel on redbull”. Popular culture would suggest meditation to mellow out the rough edges. I had always found the promises of meditation to feel too much like snake oil to trust its effectiveness. A combination of low risk, and wanting to fairly eliminate it as a useful tool, I wanted to give it an honest try. Half measures would have always felt that I may have left some stone unturned. To counter this self doubt and to give meditation the best chance of success, I decided to jump into the deep end and do a 10 day meditation course. This was done in complete silence without communicating with anyone living a monk-like existence. I figured that if the course experience was good, I would learn how to meditate correctly… and if it failed I would have gotten a 10 day break from the world. Heads I win, and tails I don’t lose; the best way to gamble 😛.</p>

<h2 id="what-did-this-involve">What did this involve?</h2>
<p>We were required to:</p>
<ul>
  <li>not talk, look at, or communicate with anyone.</li>
  <li>not read, write, or listen to any audiobook, music, or any form of entertainment.</li>
  <li>follow a frugal vegetarian diet.</li>
  <li>meditate as much as possible.</li>
  <li>Temporarily pause any daily rituals one was used to doing.</li>
</ul>

<p>The daily routine followed the schedule below:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Time</th>
      <th>Activity</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>4:00 AM</td>
      <td>Wake-Up Bell</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>4:30–6:30 AM</td>
      <td>Meditation (Hall or Room)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>6:30–8:00 AM</td>
      <td>Breakfast Break</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>8:00–9:00 AM</td>
      <td>Group Meditation in Hall</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>9:00–11:00 AM</td>
      <td>Meditation with Teacher Guidance</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>11:00 AM–12:00 PM</td>
      <td>Lunch Break</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>12:00–1:00 PM</td>
      <td>Rest / Interviews with Teacher</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>1:00–2:30 PM</td>
      <td>Meditation (Hall or Room)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>2:30–3:30 PM</td>
      <td>Group Meditation in Hall</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>3:30–5:00 PM</td>
      <td>Meditation with Teacher Guidance</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>5:00–6:00 PM</td>
      <td>Tea Break</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>6:00–7:00 PM</td>
      <td>Group Meditation in Hall</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>7:00–8:15 PM</td>
      <td>Evening Discourse by S.N. Goenka</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>8:15–9:00 PM</td>
      <td>Group Meditation in Hall</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>9:00–9:30 PM</td>
      <td>Question Time with Teacher</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>9:30 PM</td>
      <td>Lights Out / Rest</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>I’ll limit my observations to just the data that I tracked. One can find a lot more information about the Vipassana 10-day course online from others who are more verbose about philosophy, history, etc.</p>

<h2 id="physiological-changes">Physiological changes</h2>
<p>All the physiological markers mentioned here were tracked using the Garmin Phenix 6s. The graphs compare various markers for 10 days immediately preceding the retreat (in dashed-blue) with the same measurements during the retreat (in solid-blue).</p>

<h3 id="heart-rate-variability">Heart Rate Variability</h3>
<p>The most dramatic difference that I saw was in the HRV. The baseline calculated over the previous 6 weeks fluctuated between 45-70ms, but during the retreat my HRV was 122ms on average (measured as the highest 5-min average HRV).
<img src="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/e/2PACX-1vQr1aiY5KDeqZPyr3WF9ppQvZQHAvvYaXfdGeahNI-ioLExW_PfyuEefs6WR8RBX9eD6JqK-oNGd64B/pubchart?oid=2028975895&amp;format=interactive" alt="HRV tracking before and after" /></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Higher HRV indicates a relaxed and recovered state, with better adaptability to stress and fitness demands, while lower HRV suggests higher stress, fatigue, or insufficient recovery.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="resting-heart-rate">Resting heart rate</h3>
<p>For some background context: I took up running a few years ago, and one of the main reasons to do that was to improve my cardiovascular health. While training for a 2:15 half marathon, over a period of 3-6 months I saw my resting heart rate drop from 60bpm to 44bpm at its lowest. Having worn the watch consistently for the last 4 years, I have never seen it going below that number.</p>

<p>Before starting Vipassana, the 10-day average of my resting heart rate was 61.2bpm, during the 10 day retreat my average resting heart rate was 48bpm. The 10 days of meditation seem to have had the same effect as 6 months of heart training for a HM.</p>

<p>In the graph above, the blue line was the resting heart rate before going to the retreat, and the red line is my resting heart rate during the retreat. This drop to me seems like a huge change in such a short amount of time.</p>

<h3 id="sleep">Sleep</h3>
<p>Sleep is another item that I have always struggled with, and numbers measuring the duration of REM sleep that I measured were equally astonishing. On average I got almost 2.5x times the REM sleep during the days that I meditated, than what my average was for the 10 preceding days.</p>

<p>Interestingly, the deep sleep numbers saw a 20% decline. This could be attributed to the fact that I had stopped my workouts.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>REM sleep seems to be responsible for restoring cognitive function, memory, and emotional wellbeing. Deep sleep helps in physical recovery.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="subjective-changes">Subjective Changes</h2>
<p><em>(please note this last portion is primarily speculation; given that I had 10 days to think :))</em></p>

<p>My hypothesis currently is that : Vipassana (possibly meditation in general) makes it easier to let yourself have more control over the events in your periphery, and gives you a chance to practice your response.</p>

<p>This can be done from two directions:</p>
<ol>
  <li>By providing time and opportunity to re-observe events around us, and the effect they have on us.</li>
  <li>Practicing to not react to what we feel (itches etc), gives us a chance to build our response “muscles”.</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name>Sameer Kulkarni</name><email>sameer@thekulkarni.com</email></author><category term="meditation" /><category term="wellness" /><category term="quantified-self" /><category term="health" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A 10 day meditation retreat done in complete isolation showed improvements in physiological markers comparable to 6 months of training to run a 2:15 half-marathon.]]></summary></entry></feed>